So the section we're going to be kicking off right now
is on watchers and computed properties.
We've talked a lot about reactive data,
and we saw that it's cool, that it tracks.
But the next step to reactive data a lot of times
comes to the point where it's a question of what happens
when things depend on that data, right?
So you want something to happen when
the reactive data changes.
This is actually fairly common.
So granted, we're doing a lot of things automatically
at this point, right?
So for example, when the data updates view
will automatically update the HTML.
But what do we want to do more fine-grained things?
So for example, we want to watch the count up here.
And if it's even, we want to go ahead and then, say,
update the title up here to something else, right?
So you can imagine that if we had this to be counter title,
for example, and counter title would just put it here.
So counter title is going to be just a standard,
for example.
So you can see it in a fresh.
Great, counter standard here.
And we want to say we want to watch
for if the count goes past 20, then we
want to add, like, long to the text.
And so your first instinct for those who come from a framework
background is to think, well, we need to be able to watch
the thing, right?
And so to watch something in view is actually fairly simple.
There actually is a watch option, as you would expect.
So we have data, we have methods.
Here's our opportunity to watch something.
And when you want to watch something,
you basically say, what is it exactly that we're watching?
Well, in this case, we're watching the count.
And so when you actually define the count, though,
what you want to do is you want to say,
you need the value that is basically
going to return to you by default.
Because otherwise, you don't have
something to refer to inside of that value.
Because it's going to basically say, what's your new value?
What's your old value?
And so by default, you get the new value as the first one.
So let me actually just do new value like this.
So you'll see now, here we have a simple watch function
that's watching count.
And then when it changes, we should automatically see it log.
And so, ooh, do, do, do, do, watch count, did not refresh.
Refreshing would be helpful.
There we go.
OK.
So we can see here, 1826, we're getting some logs as well here
from increment count.
But we see that at least it's being triggered.
So your next thing would be like, OK, well, logically speaking,
what I would want to do then is I would say,
well, if new value is greater than 20, then this dot counter
title, ooh, counter title plus equals very long.
OK.
Now, refresh, one, two.
You can see, boom, it's updated.
And so from a mental model perspective, you're like, yeah,
that makes sense.
Cool.
And so this is actually a common paradigm in a lot of frameworks
when it comes to watching reactive dependencies.
That's what it's called.
But view has a better way for us to do this, especially when
it comes to modifying existing data.
Because if you think about what we're doing here, what we're
doing is we're saying, based on a reactive data property,
run a specific computation.
And then, but if we think about that from a performance
perspective, we really only wanted
to do that when all the dependent, like the right
dependencies are triggered.
And so one of the problems that comes with doing something
as explicitly watching values is sometimes, especially when
apps get really large, the watch can end up
getting triggered like a lot, like unnecessarily so.
And so when you hear things about people accidentally
triggering re-renders, that's what they're talking about.
It's because at that point, you're manually
watching the dependencies.
And if you don't know what you're doing,
or not caching it correctly, all of a sudden,
you might be triggering re-rendering of thousands
of nodes and whatnot.
So view, in its view fashion, came up
with an API that would help to abstract that away.
And the way it does that is through the idea
of computed properties.
And so the way computed properties worked
is basically another option on your app.
So I'm going to add it below data because,
and you'll see shortly why.
So computed properties is think of it
as basically performance optimized calculations
on reactive data that you have.
So in the instance of, for example, the counter title,
rather than it be like, OK, well, I'm
going to have a watch on this count.
If it's 20, then add the thing.
Instead, you could be, I'll say, display title, for example.
And so this will be a function that view will basically,
it will correctly decide when to run it.
So we'll see shortly.
And in this function, what are we going to do?
We're going to say, if this dot count is greater than 20,
return counter standard.
Otherwise, return, oh wait, in this case,
it was counter very long.
Otherwise, return counter standard, just like that.
And so we switch this over now to display title and refresh.
You see nothing changes, and then it's swapped,
and then it's good.
And basically, even though you might think programmatically,
this looks very similar to what we just did,
this is extremely powerful, because what you've just done
is now given view the job of figuring out
when its dependencies have changed.
And so to show you what I mean by that,
we could even combine computed properties together.
So for example, let's say that we actually
wanted to impact the increment amount based
on the length of the title.
Let's just do that.
So we could then say, let's say I call it
optimize increment amount.
And for whatever reason, we have some algorithm
that's dependent on the counter title.
What we could do is that we can return this dot display
title dot length times, and then, let's say,
this dot increment amount.
So now we have two dependencies.
We're depending on this display title here.
We're dependent on increment amount here.
But then once we update here to optimize increment amount,
we can see now that things are starting to change actually
pretty drastically.
You're seeing that the, oh, actually, I've realized you're
not actually seeing the optimize amount.
So let's show that real quick.
Where's my increment count?
OK, here we go.
Then we can say optimize increment amount.
Very good.
So you can see here it's 224 right here.
And so it's changing because why?
Because we've modified the title.
If we modify this times 10, you'll
see that now it's updating correctly by the increment
amount, but the optimize amount is now
dependent on two different things.
And so what you get with computer properties
is basically really efficient tool chaining
on reactive dependencies.
And this is a concept we're starting to see popularized.
I think Svelte has something very similar as well now,
in that if you think about an enterprise level app,
there is going to be so much that's changing.
And when you have manual definitions of what you're
watching, oftentimes you'll find that it's actually fairly
brittle because one small change will break
that entire dependency chain.
Whereas here, you can have your source of truth
being this data store, and then you
can have all your computations run off of that thing.
And it knows when to trigger, it knows what to do,
it knows how to cache it, so that in the HTML
it doesn't randomly trigger.
All that stuff that our goal is to build cool things
and to abstract business logic, deliver value to customers.
As much as it's fun to learn about performance optimizations,
that's not something we want to be debugging constantly.
And so computer properties are incredibly powerful for this.
In fact, if I were to say my single most favorite feature
of view, it's the computer property
because it just takes away all the worry for me
about what's happening, and it does so much work for me.
Again, really easy.
And it's particularly powerful if you
do any data visualizations.
You can imagine, right?
You're doing all these SVG calculations
based on a set group of data.
You don't want to have to write the dependency chain that
would update the SVG at this particular point,
and then it swaps this way or how it animates.
All that can be managed basically with computer properties.
And so some of the most elegant stores I've seen
have one source of truth inside of data,
and then they compute everything else out.
And it just works really, really well
because view can optimize all those things.